Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - to The Officers of His Majesty's Ordnance., 1779 June 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Edmund White and James Powell. St. John's, Newfoundland
    Notice that John Denny, carpenter, was entitled to draw pay for ninety-one days.
  - to The Officers of His Majesty's Ordnance., 1779 June 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Edmund White and James Powell. St. John's, Newfoundland
    List of civil officers, surgeon and artificers at St. John's.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1779. June.]; Mem.; The Continental Congress, Board of Treasury
    Schedule of sets of bills of exchange dated 1779, June 25, and payable 1782, June 15.
  - to ------ Guillaume., [1779. June.]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Strange,-----
    Has forwarded letters ot Mr. [William] Alexander at Dijon.
  - to M. Boisgerard, Merchant of Nantes., [1779]; L. 1p.; ------, -----
    Giving particulars about his vessel. "La Bouitte", captured by the English, June 15, 1778, while on voyage to America, recaptured, July 5, by Comte d'Estaing's squadron, and finally sold by the French Admiralty as a prize in April, 1779. Wishes to present a claim for reimbursement.
  - to Lord [George Germain?]., 1779 July 9; L. 4p.; Hartley, David. London
    Mortified at the unsuccessful conclusion of their late conferences reserves to himself the right of renewing the mediations as circumstances may occur; meant to provide for a shorter cast which seeme not distant then and which has since actually happened in the interference of Spain. Is still of his former opinion, notwithstanding the steps latel taken by Spain, as to the principle upon which any negotiation with America should be founded. Takes the liberty of enclosing a copy of the terms of negotiation which he lately laid before him with a alteration in the fourth article. Asks him to reconsider the enclose terms and that he might be permitted to propose a renewal of the negotiation upon them. Proposes going out of town next Monda unless he could entertain any hope that his longer stay could contribute in the least degree to facilitate the road to peace and reunion with America.
  - to Joshua Johnson, et al., 1779 July 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Paris
    He refuses to take any steps without seeing their authority for making the application, and without having a copy of the accounts in question.
  - to Louis XVI., 1779 July 10; D.S. John Jay, President. 3p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Petition for needed military and naval stores, an estimate of which the American Minister is prepared to give. Pledge repayment. Promise not to conclude peace without the concurrence of France.
  - to Richard Caswell, Governor of North Carolina., 1779 July 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Steuben, General Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Gerhard Augustin, baron von. New Windsor.
    Wrote a letter to him which he intended to send together with a copy of the "Regulations [for the Discipline of the Troops of the United States," Philadelphia: 1779], before he left Philadelphia to take charge of the army; the Board of War promised to transmit both, but sent the letter only. Is sorry for the mistake. Encloses a copy of the Regulations.
  - to Edward Bancroft, Paris., 1779 July 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Joshua. Nantes
    Introduces Nicholas Barker, of Rotterdam, and begs him to introduce Mr. Barker to Dr. Franklin.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 July 20; D.S. Morgan Jenkins, et al. 1p.; The Captain, Crew and Passengers of the Sloop, "Charlotte."
    Parole of the Captain, crew and passengers captured by the American privateer, "Black Prince," of Boston, Captain Stephen Marchant.
  - to J[ohn] D. Schweighauser., 1779 July 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the exchange of prisoners.
  - to The Principal Officers of His Majesty's Ordnance., 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Bollard, Robert. Placentia, Newfoundland
    Hopes they will be pleased to grant him the usual allowance of Twelve guineas for travelling charges, to defray the expenses of his message from St. John's to this place.
  - to [N.M.] Gellée, Passy., 1779 August 3; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Didelot, ------
    Requests him not to fail to call at his house and bring M. Darbaumont's books.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 August 6; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolution that the Commissioners and others in Europe, transmit their accounts, etc., to the Board of Treasury for settlement and that a suitable person be appointed to examine said accounts.
    Printed in Journals of Congress, Philadelphia, 1782, V, 308.
  - to James Cuming., 1779 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Sharp, William. Philadelphia
    Sends him $360 to invest in Brittany linens.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 August 9; D.S. 1p.; Neave, Richard. Passy
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 August 9; D.S. 1p.; Neave, Richard Jr. Passy
  - to Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel de Sartine., 1779 August 11; L.S. 2p.; Torris, John
    Account of a cruise of the American privateer, "Black Prince," in the Channel and off the coast of England. Brought into Brest the ship "Good Will," Capt. Power, which was condemned by the Admiralty at Brest, but, after six weeks, orders have not yet been given to have the vessel and cargo sold. The cargo is of a perishable nature and great loss is incurred by those who took the prize. Requests M. de Sartine to issue orders to allow the "Good Will" to be sold also the packet boat "Dublin," from Bristol to Dublin, captured on another cruise.
  - to Cradock Taylor, Aix., 1779 August 17; L.S. 1p.; -------, --------. Toulon
    Not surprising that he was treated as a prisoner of war, though an American subject, as he was captured in the English service. Cannot release him unless he is claimed by the American authorities or exchanged for a French prisoner held by the English.
  - to Francis Coffyn, Dunkirk., 1779 August 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Necessity of hastening the condemnation of the prizes taken by the "Black Prince"; Dr. Franklin and the Minister of Marine have both been written to on the subject, but no answer has been received.
  - to John Torris., 1779 August 27; L. 1p.; Marchant, Capt. Stephen. Brest
    Account of a cruise during which he fell in with the "Spy," tender, on the cost of Ireland, mounting fourteen nine-pounders and carrying 400 men. Gave chase and gave her five broadsides within the light-house of Waterford, but was unable to make a prize of her on that account; sprung his bowsprit in the chase. Brought eight ransomers to the amount of £2,125 10 s.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1779 August 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Rayneval, Joseph Gérard de
    Greatly astonished that Dr. Franklin has not received his packet.
  - to Mme. Dupré de St. Maur., 1779 September 4; L. 7p.; Holker, ----. Philadelphia
    M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval] and Chevalier de la Luzerne, wish him to remain here some time longer. M. Gérard is leaving for France, will take this letter and will confer with the writer's father and the Ministers about his situation here. Will abide by their decision. Is in good health and has made some tried friends. His only regret is in being separated from his family and friends in France. The state of affairs in America. The army is becoming more disciplined and effective. Comte d'Estaing's victory and the declaration of Spain in favor of France, had a good effect. Restored confidence and determination to continue the war. The alliance with France is hailed everywhere as a sure augury of final and complete independence for the Colonies. The English army in America is now confined to New York and Rhode Island. Gen. [John] Sullivan attacking the Indians on the borders of the Canadian lakes. Blunder and ignorance of the English Generals; atrocities committed by their troops. The Continental navy becoming stronger and more daring, is anxious to meet the English navy in an equal contest. The political situation in Pennsylvania very complicated, dissensions of the several parties, Whigs, Tories, Quakers, etc. Resources of the Colonies in food stuffs, etc. Finances still in a very dilapidated state. Begs to be remembered to several persons in France and in particular to Chevalier [François Jean, Marquis] de Chastellux to whom he is indebted for many favors.
  - to Cradock Taylor, Aix., 1779 September 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Frazer, Jno G. Bordeaux
    Has written to Dr. Franklin in regard to obtaining Mr. Taylor's liberty. His approaching return to America. News of Gen. [Anthony] Wayne's successful attack on a fortress near New York; hopes the next move will be against New York and Rhode Island. Capture of Grenada by Comte d'Estaing, and the good drubbing he gave Admiral [John] Byron; the Governor of Grenada's escape to Rochefort. Gives direction for his future movements, should be obtain his liberty.
  - to George Mitchell, St. Meau, in Brittany., 1779 September 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Sterling, James. Wallworth
    Sorry to find he is still a prisoner. Thinks a protection is not easily got. His brother Harry [Mitchell], in Boston, in a very good way. The latter has made Mrs. Miller's son Captain of a very fine letter of marque, and would no doubt provide for him if he could get to him. Thinks if Mitchell could get a memorial to Dr. Franklin, he would obtain liberty for him to go to Boston.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 September 25; D. 1p.; Memorandum
    List of prisoners taken by the American privateer, "Black Prince," from the British ships, "Hopewell" and "Peggy," and paroled.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 September 25; D.S. 1p.; Sterry, Cyprian. Passy
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 September 29 and October 4; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Appointment of Lieut.-Col. John Laurens as Secretary to the Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Versailles, and fixing the salary of the Minister Plenipotentiary and his Secretary.
    Printed in the Secret Journals of Congress, Boston, 1820, II, 272.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 September 29; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Appointment of Mr. Joshua Johnson to examine the accounts of Commissioners.
  - to [William] Carmichael., 1779 October 15; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hopkinson, Francis. Philadelphia
    Sends him 60 livres with which he begs him to purchase in Paris, and forward, two double sets of crayons of the first quality, and to lay out the remainder of the money at his and Dr. Franklin's discretion.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 October 15; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    In reference to supplying funds to the Ministers appointed to treat with His Catholic Majesty and with His Brittanic Majesty.
    Printed in the Secret Journals of Congress, Boston, 1820, II, 279.
  - to Cradock Taylor, Aix., 1779 October 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Frazer, John G. Bordeaux
    Will write again to Dr. Franklin to convince him that he is a native of Virginia, and a good American. Advises him to insist on not being exchanged when the cartel comes for the "Zephyr's" crew; or else to enter the French service in a merchant ship to the West Indies in any capacity, and from there be may get home immediately. Sorry he cannot help him with any more money. Is to sail next week for America.
  - to John Paul Jones., 1779 October 19; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Pearson, Captain Richard. Dallas
    Is sorry not to have been favored with either a call or line from him since his return from Amsterdam. Looks upon his behavior as a breach of that civility which his rank entitles him to. Wants to know whether steps have been taken towards the enlargement or exchange of him, his officers and people, or what is intended to be done with them. Thinks their being kept prisoners on board ship after being so long in a neutral port, a very unprecedented circumstance.
  - to Capt. [Richard] Pearson., 1779 October 20; L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Serapis," Texel
    Did not think him unacquainted with the English Ambassador's memorial of the 8th, to the States-General, and therefore thought it fruitless to pursue the negotiations for the exchange of prisoners of war now in his hands. Resents the charge of breach of civility. Knows not what difference of respect is due to rank between his service and theirs. Supposes the difference must be thought very great in England since he is informed that Capt. [Gustavus] Cuningham, of equal denomination and who bears a senior rank in the American service than his in the service of England, is now confined at Plymouth in a dungeon and in fetters. Has treated and will continue to treat the wounded with the greatest care. Encloses a copy of the Ambassador's memorial.
  - to Lieutenant James [Arthur] Degge., 1779 October 21; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Serapis," Texel
    Appoints him commander of the Continental frigate "Alliance." Instructions which he is to observe.
  - to John Paul Jones., 1779 October 22; L. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Texel
    Has received orders from Dr. Franklin to go to Paris immediately. Will leave the frigate "Alliance" to-night, in the condition he told him when he met him at Mr. Hogland's and under the care of Lieutenant [James Arthur] Degge.
  - to ------- ---------., 1779 November 12; A.L.S. 2p.; White, James. Haarlem
    Has matters of consequence to communicate to Benjamin Franklin, for which he desires a safe messenger.
  - to John Evans, Angier in Anjou., 1779 November 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Grey, R. Bristol
    Efforts to secure his enlargement. Asks him to enclose this letter to Dr. Franklin immediately and he is sure he will aid him. Sir Edward Newenham and he will stand for his bail.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 November 15; D.S. 1p.; Johnson, William. Passy
  - to David Hartley., 1779 November 15; A.L.S. 2p.; I. Bell and Robert Lulman. Office for Sick and Wounded Seamen. London
    Authorizing him to negotiate the matter of an exchange of prisoners with Dr. Franklin.
  - to David Hartley., 1779 November 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Bell, I. and Robert Lulman. Office of the Sick and Wounded Seamen, London.
    Have the Admiralty's directions for making an exchange of all the American prisoners in England. In order to facilitate this, they request him to negotiate the matter with Dr. Franklin and to procure information of the precise number of English prisoners in France; to furnish them with another pass, as they propose to send one vessel from Plymouth and another from Portsmouth, and to ascertain the name of the Agent at Morlaix with whom the exchange is to be transacted.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 November 25; 3p.; George III, King of Great Britain, 1738-1820
    Speech to both Houses of Parliament, respecting the present condition of the war, and the loyalty of the English people.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 November 26; D.S. 1p.; Harrison, Richard. Passy
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779 November 27; D. 7p.; The Assembly of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia
    An Act for vesting the estates of the late Proprietaries of Pennsylvania in this Commonwealth.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1779. November.]; Mem. 1p.; In Reference to the Descent on Ireland
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont., 1779 December 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Gillon, Alexander. Frankfort
    Is on his way to Holland. Wishes to purchase the two ships Mr. Boux built at Amsterdam. With his aid will equip them as vessels of war, and proceed to South Carolina or Virginia to take in rice, tobacco, indigo, etc. As Capt. [John Paul] Jones is now in Amsterdam, asks if they cannot unite all their interests, forces and funds so as to do something clever. Wrote to Dr. Franklin and trusts he and [Le Ray] de Chaumont may embrace the opportunity of once more aiding America.
  - to Duc de la Vauguyon., 1779 December 13; L. 4p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Texel
    Reasons why he has refused the letter of marque offered him by the French Court; would esteem himself inexcusable did he even accept a commission of equal or superior denomination to his own; astonished that the Court should offer such as insult to his understanding; contrasts this treatment with that shown to French officers by the American Ambassador.
  - to John Paul Jones, Paris., 1779 December 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Mullowney, Thomas. Ancenis
    Giving an account of his sufferings since he went on board the cutter "Surf"; is destitute of everything; begs to be assisted in his distress.
  - to [C.G.F.] Dumas., 1779 December 27; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Alliance" at Sea
    Concerning the loss of two anchors, by the "Alliance" getting foul of a Dutch merchant ship. Wishes them taken up.
  - to P. Penet., A.L. 1p.; Gruel, J. Nantes
    Arrival of Capt. Seth Paddack from America with news of the two armies in their winter quarters.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1779.]; Mem. 1p.; Anty, Louis. of Nantes
    Presents his claim against the State of Virginia for supplies furnished by him, and advances of money.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1779.]; Mem. 1p.; de Boisbertrand, Gayault
    Is Lieutenant-Colonel of Cavalry and served in the United States. Petitions to be appointed Brigadier-General in America, in consideration of his services.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779; Mem. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    "The Morals of Chess." Dr. Franklin's views of the question.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779; Mem. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Another view of the "Morals of Chess" as opposed to Franklin's view. Sets forth its disadvantages, the evils it causes and its bad effects on the mind and heart. Contends that the best players of chess are good for nothing else in life.
  - to [James] Lovell., [1779.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Penn, John, 1729-1795
    Desiring Franklin's interest on behalf of a young Virginian, Cradock Taylor, who was pressed on board an English man-of-war; his subsequent capture and imprisonment in France.
  - to John Paul Jones., L. in 3d P. 1p.; Schweighauser, John D
    Unable as yet to pay Capt. [John Paul] Jones his share of the prize-money; request that the plate [belonging to the Countess of Selkirk] should be valued.
  - to the Marquis de Lafayette, 1779; Mem. 1p.; Sword of Honor Presented by the American Congress
    Description of the emblems and figures thereon.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1779; A. Verses. 4p.; Hopkinson, Francis
    "The battle of the kegs" [1779]. Humorous account of an incident which occurred while the British were in possession of Philadelphia. "A new ballad: Date obolum Belisario" or "a penny to the poor" [1777]. Political ballad referring to England's defeat and difficulties after the war with the Colonies.
    Printed in "The Miscellaneous Essays and Occasional Writings of Francis Hopkinson, Philadelphia, 1792."
  - to John Torris, Dunkirk., 1779 June 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Marchant, Capt. Stephen. On board the "Black Prince," Morlaix Road
    Sends the name and quality of the prisoners he has taken and also the names of his men that were taken prisoners by the English on the six prizes that were retaken. The loss of his men will retard his cruise. Hopes he will use his influence to make an exchange of prisoners. Has a fine prospect before him of distressing the British. Location of their fleet.
  - to Vicomte de Rochambeau., 1779?; A.L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Note requesting the Vicomte [de Rochambeau] to see the Marquis de la Fayette and get him to obtain a prompt decision from Dr. Franklin as to the supplies of clothing for the American troops, as this is the most favorable time for buying cloth.
  - to William Bingham., 1780 January 6; L. 2p.; Governor of Guadaloupe. Bassiture
    Received orders relative to the indemnification of the owners of the brig "Fair Play." Steps taken to determine the amount.
  - to The Governor of Guadaloupe., 1780 January; L. 2p.; The Commissioners of Commerce. Bassiture
    Opinion of the Commissioners of Commerce relative to the valuation of the brig "Fair Play."
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1780 February 11; D.S. 1p.; Belt, Walter. Passy
  - to [Peter] Allaire., [1780. February 15.]; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple
    His Grandfather does not choose to grant this request [for a pass to Brussels (see p. 30)].
  - to C.G.F. Dumas., 1780 February 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Capellen tot den Pol, Joan Derk van der. Apeltern
    Complaining that his American letters are always opened, and giving an address under which he begs Dr. Franklin will forward his letters in future.
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont, Passy., 1780 March 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Paris
    Concerning the recovery of his trunks and papers left on board the "Alliance"; desires seals put upon them. Wishes to see Franklin's answer to his letter, reclaiming his belongings.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1780 March 6; D.S. 1p.; Hutchins, Thomas. Passy
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1780 March 6; Mem. 2p.; Benjamin Gale and Co. of Killingsworth, Conn
    Proposals made to any skilled manufacturer of pottery or French delph ware, who will come to America and manufacture such articles for them.
  - to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.]., 1780 March 15; L.S. 1p.; Hutchins, Thomas. Passy
    Asking that twelve of his maps and pamphlets of the interior parts of North America may be sent to Dr. Franklin.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1780 March 15; D.S. 1p.; Carpenter, Benjamin. Passy
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1780 March 25; D.S. 1p.; Fowler, Peter. Passy
  - to Joseph Belton, Paris., 1780 March 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Belton, Jonas. Groton
    Was informed by John Adams that he was in Paris. Was informed of his misfortune, by a letter from his friend, Mr. Wistmore. Would be glad of his return home.
  - to ----- Bessière., 1780 April 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Bentalon, -----. Montauban
    An account of the son of M. Prat de Figeac, who passed himself off in America as the Comte [Jules] de Montfort; procured letters from his father under this false title; determined to follow him up if possible. His principal reason for travelling in France has been to regain his strength after the wounds he received at Savannah; expects to sail from Bordeaux as soon as possible to join his regiment in America; begs for news of his friend.
  - to Isaac Cazneau., 1780 April 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Dunkin, Edmund. London
    The packet "Besbro," from Dublin to Iceland, was boarded by the Captain of the "Black Prince" who said he had an American commission and called himself [Patrick] Dowlin; he treated all the prisoners in the most savage manner; paid no attention to his order from the Massachusetts' Council; robbed him of a gold watch while his Lieutenant rifled his pockets. Asks him to inform Dr. Franklin of this, that he might be redressed.
  - to The Secretary of Dr. Franklin, Passy., 1780 April 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Besson, George Leopold. Montbéliard
    Without some assistance he and his family must perish.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1780 April 16; D.S. 1p.; Cazneau, Isaac. Passy
  - to J[ohn] Torris, Cherbourg., 1780 April 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Lefebvre, J. S
    With reference to a Dutch vessel claimed as a lawful prize. Has offered the Captain and four sailors their travelling expenses to Cherbourg. Captain refuses to go until he has received orders from Rotterdam.
  - to Chevalier de Trecesson, Martinique., 1780 April 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Peters, Richard. Philadelphia
    Is in possession of a bill for twenty-five louis, drawn on him by Dr. Franklin in the Chevalier's favor; cannot pay the money unless the bill is presented and endorsed; recommends him to Mr. William Bingham, of Martinique, to negotiate the affair.
  - to John Adams., 1780 May 5; L. 3p.; Gerry, Elbridge. Philadelphia